Chapter 7. Population Growth

   Populations of many simpler organisms, like bacteria or amebas,  grow by doubling each generation, under good conditions. The numbers of cells or individuals ( y ) depend on the number of generations ( x ), according to the equation y = 2x. It is useful to draw a graph of this, with x from 0 to 10, to show how a very small initial population can produce over 1 000 descendants (21 =2; 210 = 1 024). Of course, the time scale varies greatly with animal species, because generation time varies. The number of offspring per generation may be much more than 2 in some species. For example, a pair of fruitflies can produce 200 little flies in 2 weeks;  thus populations of Drosophila do not really double; they explode.

   As Darwin (1859) pointed out, Linnaeus had calculated that an annual plant that produces only two seeds that develop into seedlings each year can have over one million offspring after 20 years. (220 = 1 048 576)

   The doubling principle works in reverse when considering ancestors :       21 parents, 22  grandparents, 23  great-grandparents etc. With an average generation time of 30 years, about 12 generations have passed since the 17th century (1640 + 360 = 2000). Thus each person now living has 212 ancestors

from that era. Estimates of world population (Table 7-2) make it clear that the number of people living then was far too small to allow each modern individual to have an unique set of 4 096 ancestors. Therefore, it is highly probable that any two people from the same part of the world, say Norway or Mongolia, have one or more ancestors in common.

Exercise 7-1. Draw graphs of y = 2x and y = log 2x.

A good graph has scales on both the vertical (y) and horizontal (x) axes, shows all the points, and is clearly labelled. The log plot is linear, because

a logarithm is an exponent. Remember the firm rule that: when quantities with the same base are multiplied, the exponents are added.

   The number of living individuals is affected by survivorship, that is, the overlapping of generations. Future population sizes can be estimated by

subtracting death rate from birth rate. For example, in Florida in 1999, the birth rate was 13.0 live births per 1000 population, and the death rate was 10.8 per 1000. If the total population was 15 982 378, then the net increase

would be (13.0 - 10.8)/ 1000 = + 0.0022 per year.

   This predicts an increase of:

    0.0022 X 15 982 378 = 35 161 people added by the following year.

   Population growth rates can be expressed as the ratio of present census to an earlier one. For example, the population of Sarasota County, FL was    277 776 in 1990, and 325 957 in 2000. The growth rate was:  325 957 / 277 776 = 1.17348871;    1.17348871 – 1 = +17.35% in 10 years = 1.735%/yr.

      In the same years, the population of Newark, NJ changed from 275 221 to 273 546. The rate was negative:

          0.993913981 -1 = -0.006086019 in 10 years = - 0.0609%/yr.

Perhaps 1 675 people moved from Newark to Sarasota in that decade. (If so, they made a good decision.) These population changes may be compared to the increase in the entire USA. The first census was done in 1790. and it was repeated every ten years since then (Table 7-1).

Exercise 7-2. Calculate the percentage change of USA population from 1990 to 2000.

    This result suggests that Sarasota population grew more rapidly than the average for the whole country.

Exercise 7-3. Make a graph of USA population (y) vs years (x) from 1790 to 1890: then make a graph of log y. Your graphs should resemble Fig. 7-1.

    These graphs look much like the graphs of y =2x (Exercise 7-1), and suggest doubling, or some other exponential process, like money at compound interest. Thanks to calculus, it is possible to derive an equation, similar to the compound-interest equation, which allows calculation of annual growth rates, and projections of future populations.

    The basic equation is:  dN/dt = rN, where N is number, t is time, and r is a rate constant. As Banks (1998) wrote, “the rate at which a particular quantity grows is directly proportional to the amount of the quantity present at any moment.”

    The problem is to obtain r from counts taken at two times. In ecology, r is a natural rate of increase, a characteristic of a species when its population growth is unrestrained.  To obtain r from census data, the basic equation must be transformed into one that allows calculation. By a theorem of calculus, the process of integration yields :

                                              Nt/No =  ert

No  is the  initial number; Nt is the number at time t;  e is a constant, the base   of the system of natural logarithms is symbolized ln rather than log. The logarithmic form of the equation above is:

                                        r = (ln Nt - ln N0) / ∆t

    Remember that log refers to logarithms of  the base 10. A LOGARITHM IS AN EXPONENT.  e is an irrational number, approximately 2.718. Your scientific calculator will give you a more precise value of e. Because the base is smaller, the ln of a number is about 2.3 times the log of the number.

    Now, let us find r for a particular population. In 1995, the population of Pakistan was 131.5 million, and in the year 2000, it was 144.6 million.

      r = (ln 144.6 - ln 131.5)/ 5 y = (4.97397131 – 4.879006852)/ 5

         = 0.094964458/5 = 0.01899/y = 1.899 % per year

   Note the similarity to a calculation of  rate of appreciation of property (Chapter 6). The main difference is the use of  base e, rather than base 10 logarithm. The compound-interest equation seems a variant of this more fundamental equation.

Exercise 7-4. Calculate r of USA for two 50-year periods, 1790-1840, and 1950-2000, from the two pairs of census data (Table 7-1).

   This result shows a much more rapid population growth in the early history of  the country. Was it due to immigration, or a very high birth rate, or both?

In ecology, r is often a maximum rate, observed when population growth is unrestrained by environmental factors. For humans, this is about 3.0% per year.

    Future populations can be predicted by using the most recent r value, according to a different form of the same equation:

                                  ln Pt = ln P0 + r∆t

To predict the population of Pakistan in 2005:

       ln Pt = ln 144.6 + 0.01884 X 5 y = 5.06817131

Use the ex function to find Pt = 158.9 million.

Exercise 7-5. (a) Use the data of Table 7-2 to draw a graph of world population, and a graph of the natural logarithm of the same numbers.  The curves are expected to resemble Fig. 7-2. (b) Predict world population in the year 2020, based on r for the interval 1980-2000.

   This predicts a year 2020 population very much greater than the year 2000, and  raises the question of saturation level or carrying capacity of the earth. One view is that the more people the better; advances in agriculture and engineering can always supply more food and water. The only real problem is distribution. Another view is that a finite earth cannot support an unlimited number of people, and the earth is already dangerously overpopulated. Thus, ways to limit population growth must be found. Which is correct?

Chapter 6. Compound Interest

   Two young people leave their homes to become students at a distant school. Each has received the same advice that Polonius gave his son Laertes: ''Neither a borrower nor a lender be, For loan oft loses both itself and friend, And borrowing dulleth th'edge of husbandry.'' (Husbandry is careful or thrifty management.) Good advice, but away from parental guidance, one becomes a borrower and the other a lender.

   Mike throws a party for all his new friends, and charges the food and drink on his credit card. Added to his travel and car expenses, the bill is staggering, so he pays the minimum, and ''carries a balance'' of $1 000. In effect, Mike has borrowed $1 000 from the bank that issued the card.

   Jennifer receives a scholarship check from an organization in her home town, and deposits $1 000 in a savings account at the same bank, making her, in effect, a lender. The consequences can be expressed in terms of compound interest paid by Mike, and received by Jennifer.

In the compound interest equation, P is the principal, the amount on which the calculation of interest is based; S is the sum that results from the calculation; i is the interest rate; n is the number of days, quarters, or years.

                                          S = P ( 1 + i )n

   The credit card bill that Mike receives after 30 days shows S, the amount he owes. The interest charged on this particular card has an annual rate (APR) of 10.240%. Percent means “per hundred”, so 10% = 0.10 in ordinary numbers. The daily rate is:

         i = 0.1024/ 365 days/year = 0.00028050547/day

Use the yx key (or xy) to calculate an exponential quantity.

S = $1 000 (1.00028050547) 30 = $1 000 (1.008450766) = $1 008.45

Mike now owes $1 000 plus $8.45 interest.

   Jennifer finds interest credited to her account after 30 days. It was calculated with APR = 1.25%;

i = 0.0125/365 = 0.000034246/day

(Step missing here. Can you supply it?)

S = $1 000 X 1.0010279 = $1 001.0279

Her account has grown by $1.03. Compare with the interest paid by Mike. Have you ever wondered why there are so many banks?

Exercise 6-1.

1. Another depositor has a balance of $16 159 in the same type of account as Jennifer. Calculate the amount of interest she receives after 30 days.

2. This woman decides to put the $16 159 into a certificate of deposit that credits interest quarterly, at an annual rate = 3.81% compounded. How much interest does she receive in one year (4 quarters)?

   Rates of gain or loss in the value of property can be found with a modification of the compound-interest equation, by taking the logarithm of both sides, and rearranging:

      S = P ( 1 + i )n

      log S = log P + n log (1 + i )

The logarithm of a number is the power of 10 equivalent to that number :

                        1 000 = 103                log 1 000 = 3.

 Repeat after me: A logarithm is an exponent . A logarithm is an exponent.

In the original equation, n is an exponent. Taking logs brings it down to earth, into an ordinary number position .

Next, rearrange:

       log (1+i) = (log S - log P) / n

After finding the value of log (1+i),  use the antilog or 10x function on the calculator to find 1+i. Then merely subtract 1 to get i, the rate of appreciation or depreciation.

   For example, a homeowner sells his property for $500 000; he bought it 16 years before for $110 000.

      log (1+i) = (log 500 000 - log 110 000)/ 16 y

      = (5.698970004 - 5.041392685)/16 =  0.041098582

      1+i = antilog 0.041098582 = 1.099255336

       (Subtract 1.)

       i = 0.0992/year = 9.92%/yr

   Of course, this apparent rate of appreciation is partly due to inflation, which has varied from 1.3 to 2.9 percent per year in recent years.

   Mike's car was bought 8 years ago for $9 950, and now has a book value of $2 210.  He has appreciated having a car, but the car has not appreciated.  The depreciation rate is:

       log 1+i = -0.653430807/8y = -0.08167885

       1+i = 0.828554631,  i = -0.171445368/yr

His car has depreciated at a rate of 17.1% per year, an asset to his social life, but a  poor investment.

   Shares of stock in corporations tend to increase in value in the long run (Fig. 6-1). Average selling prices, representative of the stock market in general, are reported as S&P 500, Dow-Jones, etc. Over some periods, your investment grows rapidly, especially if you re-invest dividends instead of spending them. The compound interest equation allows calculation of the rate of appreciation. The graph shows that $1 invested in 1926 grew to

$2 053 in 2001:

      log(1+i) = (log 2 053 - log 1) / 75 = 0.044165185

                           1+i = antilog 0.044165185 = 1.107044774

                                            i = 0.1070 = 10.7 % per year

Not bad, but who wants to wait 75 years, in this age of instant gratification?

Exercise 6-2. Jennifer receives $10 000 from her rich uncle at her graduation,

when she is 22. Instead of paying off student loans, she invests in stocks. If her shares appreciate 10.7%/yr, what are they worth when she is 50?

  The logarithm of a number is the power of 10 equivalent to that number.   Here is a nice theorem that illustrates the meaning of logarithm and the meaning of proof:

                          THE LOGARITHM OF 2 IS IRRATIONAL.

   By irrational we mean that it cannot be expressed as a ratio of whole numbers, such as ¼, ½, ¾ etc. By logarithm we mean that this ratio, if it exists, serves as the exponent of 10.

   Assume that such a ratio of two numbers p and q exists:

                                        log 2 = p/q

                                        10 p/q = 2

Raise both sides to the q power:           (pq /q = p)

                                         10 p  =  2 q

This is impossible, because all powers of 10 end in 0, and all powers of 2 end in 2, 4, 6, or 8. Therefore, the assumption is wrong. Such a ratio cannot exist. QED.

   Quod erat demonstrandum = “Which was to be demonstrated”, a Latin phrase signifying that the proof is complete.

   There are ratios, such as 31/103 and 497/1651, almost the same as log 2, but “not exactly”. QED also stands for quantum electron dynamics.  Avoid this usage, unless you love physics.

Chapter  9. Molecules.

   Every material object or substance consists of atoms and molecules. For the most part, they are too small to be seen, but quantitative chemical  evidence for their existence is overwhelming. As Linus Pauling wrote, “Atoms are the units which retain their identity when chemical reactions take place.”  To appreciate events in the natural world, including functions of  the human body, you (yes, you) must have some minimal knowledge of atoms and molecules. Even the artistic-creative and poetic sort need this.

   A chemical element consists of atoms of only one kind; there are 92 natural elements, with names like hydrogen, oxygen, carbon, nitrogen, each with a symbol such as H, O, C, N. A chemical compound consists of atoms of more than one kind, such as H2O = water, CO2 = carbon dioxide, NH3 = ammonia. These formulas represent molecules of compounds.  Symbols such as O2 – oxygen or N2 – nitrogen  represent molecules composed of two atoms of the same element. Molecules are very small, but some are sufficiently large that images of them can be made with special equipment. Now, the concept of atoms and molecules is beginning to make sense to you.

    Analysis of the composition of molecules formed in chemical reactions has enabled chemists to put the elements in order of atomic number in a chart called the periodic table. This is printed in many textbooks. Real chemists have it in their heads. The word atom means indivisible, but atomic physics has shown that atoms actually have a very dense nucleus of protons and neutrons, surrounded by a lot of space with fast-moving electrons. Chemical reactions are the result of behavior of the outer electrons.  Atomic numbers are equal to the number of protons in the nucleus of all atoms of a specific element, while the sum of protons and neutrons determines the atomic weight. These simple facts sound like dogma, and they are. However, their origin is not revelation, but rather the result of many experiments in many laboratories. If you want to get to the bottom of this dogma, take a chemistry course, and question the instructor.

   Chemists are fond of a quantity called the mole, which is the molecular weight (MW) of a substance, taken in grams. The molecular weight is the sum of the atomic weights of the atoms forming the molecule. For example, one mole of water weighs 18 g: 2 H = 2,  O = 16,  H2O =18; one mole of carbon dioxide weighs 44 g: C = 12, 2 O = 32, CO2 = 44.

Exercise 9-1. Determine the MW of carbonic acid, H2CO3. What is the MW of cholesterol, C27H52O ?

   Now, consider  some really big and really small numbers. The number of                                                                      molecules in a mole = 6.02 X 10 23 ; this was determined by experiments  that were followed by calculations based of the charge of an electron:                      1.60 X 10-10  coulomb.

   Hey, Jennifer, what is the charge on a mole of electrons? Oh, Mike, that is so easy!           6.2 X 10 23 ( 1.60 X 10-10) = 9.632 X 1013 coulombs.

Note that when numbers like this are multiplied, the exponents are added. When one number is divided by another, the lower (divisor) exponent is subtracted from the upper (dividend) to get the answer (quotient). If a mole of water weighs 18.0 g, how much does each molecule weigh?

                18.0 X 100g / 6.02 X 1023 = 2.99 X 10-23 g

There is no way to isolate one molecule of water, nor any balance to weigh it. Such questions are really just a way to have fun with numbers.  Other than a wish to communicate with numbers freaks, is there any reason to be familiar with the rules of exponents? With the US national debt in the trillions of dollars, and world population over six billion, the answer is yes.

                                              106 = 1 million =                1 000 000

                                              109 = 1 billion =          1 000 000 000

                                              1012 =  1 trillion = 1 000 000 000 000

The confusion associated with long strings of zeroes is eliminated.

Numbers with negative powers of ten express small quantities, and are reciprocals of the large numbers as follows:

                            10-6 = 1/ 106 = 0.000 001 = 1 one-millionth part

                            10-9 = 1/ 109 = 0.000 000 001 = 1 one-billionth part

   In chemistry, it is often more convenient to work with less than one mole of a substance, and a terminology has developed to describe extra small amounts, such as chemicals in blood, or pollutants.

 10-3 mole is a millimole = mmol

 10-6 mole = 1 micromole = mmol

A micromole is not a tiny burrowing mammal. Molar does not refer to a tooth. Molar refers to concentration: a 1 molar solution of C6H12O6  (MW 180.156) contains 180 grams dissolved in 1 liter. The label on the bottle reads 1.0 M glucose.

   The blood plasma of a healthy fasting adult contains 0.910 g glucose / L. The molar concentration is:                                                                                                         0.910 g / 180.156 g/mol = 5.05 X 10-3 M = 5.05 mM.

Exercise 9-2. In a glucose tolerance test, a diabetic patient had a fasting level of 1.290 g/L, and a maximum of 2.620 g/L. Express these concentrations in mM.

   Below 10 -6- micro are additional prefixes: 10-9 - nano, and 10-12 - pico. A normal plasma concentration of insulin, the hormone that regulates blood sugar, may range up to 500 picomolar:

                     500 pM = 500 X 10-12 M = 0.5 X 10-9 M = 0.5 nM

   Hormones are highly effective at very low concentrations. With MW =      5 808, a 1M solution of insulin would contain 5 808 g/L, an obvious impossibility, because 5.8 kg cannot dissolve in 1 kg water. On the other hand, 500 pM = 0.5 nM = 0.5 X 10-9 X 5.808 X 103 = 2.9 X 10-6 g/L.

This is a measurable concentration, 2.9 mg/L.

Exercise 9-3. The normal level of cholesterol is 2.00 g / L plasma. With the molecular weight determined in Exercise 9-1, convert this number into a molar concentration.

Clinical laboratories use both mg/dL and mM to express concentrations of substances in blood and urine. The results of testing your fluids should state the units of concentration. Do not pay for diagnostic tests unless the results  are stated properly.

Chapter  10. Population decline

    Some natural processes show an exponential decrease, rather than an  increase.  An important type of exponential decrease is shown by the decay rate of radioactive materials.

    Element number 84, the first radioactive element, was discovered by Marie Curie, a Polish chemist working in Paris. She named it Polonium.   All of the elements from 84 to 92 are radioactive, which means that they are unstable, and break down spontaneously, emitting particles and rays. The atoms disintegrate on a predictable schedule, not according to the age of individual atoms, but according to the total present at any moment. The decay process is a statistical process, which can be described by equations like the population growth equations, but with a negative rate constant.

   The first radioactive element isolated was radium, separated from uranium ore by Marie (Fig. 10-1) and Pierre Curie in 1898. (Pierre taught her French, and she taught him Polish.) The decay process is symbolized by:

                                  88Ra226  ----->  86Rn222  +  a                                       The products are a radon atom and an alpha particle, which consists of 2 protons and 2 neutrons, thus accounting for both the decrease of 2 in atomic

number and the decrease of 4 in atomic weight.The rate of decay is:

                                              dN/dt = lN

N is number of atoms;  l is a rate constant that is negative.

The same rearrangement and integration used in Chapter 7 yields:

                                        l = (ln Nt - ln N0) /Dt

 The decay constant can be calculated from the weight of the Curie sample, which was originally 200.0 mg, and 100 years later weighed 191.62 mg.

            l = (ln 191.62 - ln 200.0) / 100y = - 0.042803122 / 100y =

                           -0.00042803122/y =  - 4.28 X 10-4/y

 The decay constant is an important factor in the use of radioactivity in  tracer experiments, radiation therapy, and dating of ancient artifacts. Another  useful constant is called the half-life, which applies to a chemist who needs to get a life. No, not really. It is the time to lose one-half of the original radioactivity, and is related to the decay constant. For the radium sample, the calculation is:

                 t1/2  = ln 0.5/ l =  -  0.69314718 / - 4.28 X 10-4  = 1620 years

     All of the atoms of a single element are not identical. They all have the same number of protons and electrons, and therefore the same atomic number, and the same chemistry. However, variation in the number of neutrons results in different kinds of atoms of the same element, called isotopes. For example, most carbon atoms are C-12, but there are three other isotopes. The abundances are C12 = 98.9%,  the heavy isotope C13 = 1.1 %, and very small  quantities of C11 and C14, both radioisotopes.

   C-11 has been produced from boron by bombardment with deuterons in a cyclotron. The reaction is symbolized by:

                                          5B10 (d,n) 6C11

C11 decays back to boron, and the emitted positron can be detected by the appropriate radiation counter. Until the atoms disintegrate, they behave chemically just like ordinary C-12 carbon.

                                    C11 ----->  B11 + b+

Exercise 10-1. The decay constant of C11 is  l = - 0.0340/ min. Calculate the half-life.

   This result indicates that experiments with C11 must be completed quickly, or the radioactivity will decay to the point where there is too little to measure. The general rule is a limit of 8 times the half-life, in this case only 2 hours 43 minutes. On the other hand, C14  has such a long half-life, 5730 years, that any spillage will contaminate the lab practically forever.

   Small amounts of C14 are continuously produced in the atmosphere by cosmic-ray bombardment of nitrogen. C-14 is produced in the laboratory by irradiation of N-14 with neutrons in a nuclear reactor, by the same n,p reaction.

                                                      7N 14 (n,p) 6C14

  (The subscript numbers 7 and 6 are superfluous, because every chemist   knows that nitrogen is element 7 and carbon is element 6.)                                                        The decay is by emission of beta particles, which are fast-moving electrons:

                                     C14 -----> N14 + b-

    Carbon-14 has been extremely useful in tracing pathways of metabolism,   especially in photosynthesis studies, and in some aspects of medical research.

     Important to archeologists was the use of C-14 by Willard F. Libby to determine the age of prehistoric artifacts. This radioactive isotope is present

at very low concentration in the CO2 of the air. Carbon dioxide is used by plants to make sugars, starches, and cellulose. C-14 enters the bodies of animals that eat plants. When living things die, they are removed from the carbon cycle, the C14 is no longer replenished, and it continues to decay. Thus, the samples of ancient wood, charcoal, and bone have less radioactivity than modern materials. Special apparatus, consisting of very sensitive detectors and heavy shielding, were built to record these extremely low levels of radiation.

 Exercise 10-2. Given the half-life of C-14 as 5730 years, calculate the decay constant.

The decay constant l can be used in the same way as the growth constant r in the population-growth equation, to calculate age of the sample counted:

The basic equation describing the process is:

                                      Dt = (ln Nt - ln  N0) / l

   For example, a sample of charcoal taken in 2000 from the late Neolithic Stonehenge site (Fig. 10-2) had C14 radioactivity = 7.96 counts per minute (c/m) per gram carbon. Modern samples of material from living organisms average 13.56 c/m per g C.

                  Dt = (ln 7.96 - ln 13.56) / - 0.000120968/ y =

                  -0.532695282/ - 0.000120968/y = 4 403.6 years before present

This makes the age of the Stonehenge site:  2000 - 4 404 = 2404 BC.

     The Lascaux cave in the Dordogne region of France has many paintings  made by a Paleolithic artist, including the long-extinct bison (Fig. 10-3).

Exercise 10-3. Using the modern radioactivity figure above, find the age of a sample of bone from the Lascaux cave that had 2.075 c/m per g C.

    Civilization had developed in Mesopotamia and Egypt long before Stonehenge, but some of the artifacts are less ancient. The funerary boat of Sesostris III (Fig. 10-3) was found in his burial chamber inside the pyramid near Dahshur, Egypt. A piece of wood, probably cedar, from the boat was obtained from the Chicago Natural History Museum by Dr. Lilly in 1949, and was analyzed for C-14 age.

Exercise 10-4. Assuming 13.56 dpm/g C for modern wood, and 8.56 for the  sample, calculate age of the boat.

   Willard F. Libby received a Nobel prize in 1960, published a book on radiocarbon dating in 1965, and died in 1980.

   The C-14 method cannot be used for dating fossils, remains of organisms that lived millions of years ago. Some of these have been dated by the K40 method. Many minerals contain potassium, and are found in the sedimentary rocks in which fossils are embedded. K40 has two decay products, Ca40 and Ar40, so the analysis is complicated, requiring assumptions about the original quantity of K. Data from mass spectrometer analysis of a sample of mica from the Cambrian indicates N0 = 0.0741 mg of K40, and present Nt = 0.0541 mg. The decay constant is:  l = 5.501 X 10-10 / y.

     Dt = (ln 0.0541 - ln 0.0741) /  5.501 X 10-10/ y = 0.0571862 X 1010 y

                 = 570  X 106 = 570 million years

   Geologists agree that this is the correct age for the Cambrian, the earliest period with abundant animal fossils. About half of the known Cambrian fossils are trilobites, beautiful marine animals that became totally extinct in the Permian period.

Exercise 10-5. With the value of l above, calculate the age of the trilobite Ctenopyge (Fig.10-4) from rock that now contains 0.05490 mmol K40, and originally contained 0.07308 mmol.

   The time scale of the geological periods and epochs has been established  through the use of radioactive elements of known half-life.

    The decrease in sunlight with ocean depth also proceeds exponentially, as if each successive tiny layer were absorbing the same small fraction of light reaching it from above.  Here are measured fractions of blue-green light at various depths:

  surface                  1.0

   5 m                      0.581                                                                                                          10 m                       0.338

 21.2                       0.100

 42.4                       0.010

 50.4                       0.0042

 63.5                       0.0010

 Exercise 10-6. Draw a graph of fractional light intensity (y) vs depth in meters (x).  Calculate a decay constant from the fractions at 10m and 21.2m.

    Survival of  humans decreases rapidly after age 75. A college alumni directory contains the names of all male alumni from each class. From this list, and the number of those whose deaths have been reported, an average fraction of those surviving to each year can be calculated.

                         age              fraction living

                         25               1.0

        35               1.0                                80           0.3962

        47               0.9766                          83           0.2586

        60               0.9296                          91           0.1304

        68               0.867                            97           0.0385

                         76              0.7857                         100           0.02564

        78               0.4925                        108           0.01613

                                                              110           0

 Exercise 10-7. Draw graph of fraction living (y) vs age (x), then a second graph of ln y vs x.

    Note the similarity between the graph of light in the ocean and the graph   of survival after age 76.

Chapter 11. Pressures

   Everyone is under pressure - atmospheric pressure outside, and blood pressure inside. Pressures of work and family life are not readily quantified: see your psychotherapist about them.

   Atmospheric pressure is due to the weight of the air, which varies a little from day to day, and decreases with altitude. Ordinarily noticed only by mariners and weather people, it is measured by a barometer. The simplest type of barometer is a tube of some liquid inverted, mouth down, in an open dish of the same liquid. The column falls, leaving a vacuum at the top of the tube. It remains high because of the atmospheric pressure on the surface of the liquid in the dish. The favorite liquid is mercury, a metallic element that has a very high density, and is in the liquid state at ordinary environmental temperatures. ('udrarguros = quicksilver = mercury = Hg).

   The height of the column of mercury supported by the weight of the atmosphere is usually just over ¾ meter, or 760 mm (Figure 11-1). This apparatus is so simple that it is tempting to express all pressures in mm Hg, but this is a naïve, unscientific way of thinking about pressures.  Automobile tires are marked with maximum inflation pressures in psi (pounds per square inch) and kPa (kilopascals), but not in mm Hg. The relation of these units is worth examining. If the tire pressure is 44 psi, the first step is to convert one     pound into kilograms:

  1lb/ 2.20462 lbs = x/ 1 kg,   x = 0.453592909 kg

    Pressure is a force, and a force is the product of mass and acceleration:

f = ma.  Thank you, Sir Isaac.

The acceleration of gravity  a = 9.80665 m / s2.   Therefore:

       f = 0.453592909  kg  X  9.80665 m / s2 =  4.448226905 kg- m / s2

         = 4.448 Newtons

    The next step is to find the area subject to this force:

   1 inch / 39.37 in/m = 0.0254 m,    1 in2 = (0.0254 m)2 = 0.000645162 m2

    4.448 N / 0.000645162 m2 = 6894.744119 N/ m2

     The unit of force with these SI dimensions is called the Pascal, after a Frenchman who studied the meaning of pressure, among other things. This unit is too small for most measuring devices, so the usual practice is to deal with the unit 1 000 times larger, the kiloPascal (kPa). The result above can be expressed as 1 psi =  6.8947 kPa. Thus 44 psi = 303.3668 kPa. On the tire,

this is rounded off to 300 kPa.

Exercise 11-1. (a) Atmospheric pressure is 760 mm Hg or 14.696 psi. Convert psi to kPa.  (b) Use 760 mm,  density of mercury = 13.595 g/cm3, and the acceleration of gravity above, and calculate 1 atmosphere in kPa. (This is rather challenging because of the mixture of units, but give it a try.)

   The answer to both calculations should be the same:

                        1 atm = 760 mm Hg = 14.695 psi = 101.32 kPa.

Tire inflation pressures and blood pressures are actually the amounts that they exceed atmospheric pressure.

Exercise 11-2. Typical blood pressures are still given as 120 systolic and 80 diastolic. To agree with modern practice, convert these mm Hg into kPa.

   Breathing is accomplished by changing pressure on the air in the lungs, causing inhaling and exhaling. Gases expand and contract when pressure is varied. This is evident in hot-air balloons, tanks of compressed gases, and compression in the cylinders of gasoline and diesel engines.  The behavior of gases in response to changes in pressure and temperature is described by a beautiful equation:

                                       pV = nRT.

n is number of moles;  to simplify calculation, n is taken as 1 mole, and p is counted in atmospheres rather than kPa. V is volume, T is temperature in degrees Kelvin, and R is the ideal gas constant = 0.0821026 L-atm / mol-deg.  Standard  conditions are 1 atm and  273oK = 0o C. Therefore the volume of 1 mole of any gas is:

                                     V = RT / p = 0.0821026  X  273  = 22.414 L.

One mole of nitrogen (N2) weighs 28 grams, O2 - 32 g, CO2 - 44 g , H2 only 2 g. All occupy the same space. In trying to picture this volume, think of a cube 28.2 cm on each edge: 28.23 = 22 426 cm3, about the size of a bread- box, or the box containing the chips and circuits of a computer, measuring

 32 X 39 X 18 = 22 464 cm3.

   Equations for distance - time - speed, and voltage across a resistance, like the ideal gas equation, have the simple form y = a x. As Cromer wrote, “None of the linear relations of elementary physics is exactly true.”  At very high pressures, the volume decrease is less than predicted by V = RT / p.

In order to make the equation match the data of experiments, a parameter is introduced:

                                           p (V - b) = nRT.

For example, 1 mole of hydrogen under 500 atm  proved to have volume  0.060524 L. The expected volume was: 22.414 L / 500 atm  = 0.044828 L.

The difference observed sets the value of the parameter b.

       b = Vobs – Vexp =  0.060524 – 0.044828 = 0.015696 L

Exercise 11-3. A mad physicist found that his machine could produce

a pressure of 1000 atm on a gas. When he subjected 1 mole of  hydrogen

to this pressure, its volume was reduced to 0.038255 L. Calculate b.

   This parameter represents volume occupied by the molecules themselves, called the volume of exclusion or incompressible volume. Deviations from “ideal gas” behavior also occur due to attraction between gas molecules,

which tends to make volumes a little less than expected, and requires an

additional parameter. As a talk-show host said, “Anyone who uses the word parameter in ordinary conversation should not be invited to a dinner party.”

Chapter 12. Gene frequency.

   The best-studied human genes are those that produce medical problems, such as hemolytic anemia in newborn. The Rhesus system is a set of antigens on red blood cells, of which the D agglutinogen is the strongest. It causes trouble when the mother is Rh-negative, and the fetus has inherited the D factor from the father. The immune system of the mother identifies the fetus as foreign, and produces antibodies that cause destruction of the fetal red cells. People may marry without inquiring into each other's blood types.

   The symbol DD represents the genotype of someone who has received the D gene from both parents; the symbol dd indicates the genotype of a person lacking the antigen, known as Rh-negative (Rh-); the symbol Dd stands for the heterozygous or hybrid individual. In the blood donation center, DD and Dd people are lumped together as positives (Rh+). In the US, Rh+ people make up 85 percent of the population, and Rh- the other 15 percent.

   The frequency of the genes D and d in a population can be calculated from the phenotypic numbers by means of the Hardy-Weinberg rule. This principle was discovered independently by G. H. Hardy, a mathematician, and S. Weinberg, a physician. Call the frequency of the dominant gene p, and the frequency of the recessive allele q. Then, by random mating, the frequencies of the genotypes are:

                                            (p + q)2 = p2 + 2pq + q2

This is called the expansion of a binomial. You learned this in Algebra 1.    In the case of the Rh factor, q2 is the same as the fraction of Rh- people, stated above as 0.15. The gene frequencies are calculated as follows:

                                           q2 = 0.15       q = √0.15  = 0.387298334

                                             p = 1 - q = 0.612701665

This result allows calculation of the fractions of the two Rh+ genotypes.

                                          DD = p2 = ( 0.6127)2 = 0.3754

                                           Dd = 2 pq = 2 X 0.6127 X 0.3873 = 0.4746

Adding the dd fraction 0.15 makes the total 1.0, or 100 percent, as expected.

Exercise 12-1. In some Asian populations, the fraction of dd individuals has been reported as only 1 percent. Assuming exactly 0.010, calculate the gene frequencies p and q.

   Gene frequencies may change as a result of mutation or selection or migration. As W. F. Ganong wrote, “In general, harmful mutations tend to die out, but mutant genes that confer traits with survival value persist and spread in the population.”  In effect, he stated the essence of human evolution.

   The gene for sickle-cell anemia produces a modified hemoglobin molecule, which causes red blood cells to assume an abnormal sickle or crescent shape at low oxygen concentrations (Fig. 12-1). People with genotype ss are severely affected, those with Ss have few symptoms, and those with the dominant genotype SS are normal.  In some populations of equatorial Africa, sickle-cell anemia patients (ss) amount to 1 in 64 or more (0.015625), and people with the trait (Ss) up to 40%. Call the frequency of S, the normal allele, a, and call the frequency of s, the harmful mutant gene, b.  Applying the Hardy-Weinberg rule:

                b2 = 0.01562,   b = √0.01562 = 0.12498,    a = 1 - b = 0.8750

These frequencies can be used to calculate the fractions of each class:

 Phenotype         Genotype          Frequency         Observed         Expected

   normal             SS                       a2                      0.58                0.765625

   carrier              Ss                      2ab                     0.40                0.218715

   afflicted           ss                        b2                       0.01562

This result suggests that the observed fraction of carriers (Ss) is too high, and normal (SS) too low. Something is disturbing the genetic equilibrium.

Exercise 12-2. Calculate the expected gene frequencies in the African-American population, with the disease 1 in 500,  and the trait 1 in 12, using the reasoning and steps above.

  In this case, the observed and expected are not far apart. What is different in Africa and America?  Many things, but the explanation seems to lie in the prevalence of malaria.  The abnormal hemoglobin hampers the rapid growth of the malarial parasite in the bloodstream, conferring a selective advantage on those with the sickle-cell trait, when they live in a region where malaria

is prevalent. Such regions are common in central Africa, uncommon in USA.

   A successful blood transfusion requires matching ABO blood types of donor and recipient. Everyone has one of the four types, A, B, O, or AB, genetically determined, and unaltered through life. In an incompatible transfusion, the donor is not harmed, but his red cells encounter antibody in the recipient's bloodstream, which causes them to agglutinate and block capillary circulation. Inheritance gives each person two out of the set of three genes, two of which, A and B, are co-dominant. The genes are designated

IA, IB, and i, for their role in producing isoagglutinogens.

                   Phenotypes                  Genotypes                   Fraction in USA

                       A                                 IAIA, I Ai                        0.41

                       B                                 IBIB, IBi                         0.10

                       O                                    ii                                 0.45

                       AB                               IAIB                                         0.04

    If the gene frequencies are symbolized by p, q, and r, and the Hardy-Weinberg rule applies, then the fractions of the genotypes in a population should correspond to the expansion of a trinomial:

                          (p + q + r)2 = p2 + 2 pq + q2 + 2 pr + 2 qr + r2

            r2 = (frequency of ii) = fraction of type O in population = 45% in USA

                                r2 = 0.45    r = √0.45 = 0.670820393

Type A corresponds to the terms of the expansion p2 + 2 pr, and occurs in about 41% of people in the US. But we already have r, and we recognize, because of our familiarity with basic algebra, that p can be found, since:

   (p + r)2 = p2 + 2pr + r2 = 0.41 +  0.45 = 0.86 = total of type A and type O.

        p + r = √0.86 = 0.927361849        p = 0.92736  - 0.67082 = 0.25654

Since the sum must equal 1:   q = 1 - (p + r) = 1 - 0.92736 = 0.07263815

With the frequencies p, q, and r known, the expected fractions of types B and AB can be calculated, and compared with the reported fractions.

Type B:     q2 + 2 qr = (0.07263815)2 + 2 X 0.072638 X 0.67082 = 0.10273

Type AB:    2pq = 2 X 0.25654 X 0.072638 = 0.03727

   These results agree with the 10% and 4% listed above, and indicate a genetic equilibrium, sometimes called a balanced polymorphism. The fraction of people who are both AB and Rh-negative is:

    0.03727 X 0.15 = 0.0055905, or about 56 in 10 000.

Exercise 12-3.  The percentages of blood types in Japan are: O = 30, A = 38, B = 22, and AB = 10. Find the gene frequencies by the procedure shown here, and determine whether the fractions B and AB are consistent with the data.

   Young couples in Japan have been reported to compare blood types when they first meet. Do not laugh; some of our own young people consider signs of the zodiac when choosing a potential mate.

Chapter 13. Energy

   Energy and mass are the most basic concepts of physics. As new discoveries are made about energy transformations, the results are put in the form of equations. Physics without math is like marriage without sex, or breakfast without coffee. The main reason that the newer physics of relativity is not well understood is that many people do not know the old physics. Einstein did not discard classical physics; he modified it to describe events inside of atoms and in outer space. For events between these extremes, Archimedes and Newton do very well, thank you.

   Both energy and mass are conserved; within a closed system, there is no net gain or loss. When a home run is hit, there is a loss of the mass of one baseball, because it has left the system. When a hot dog is eaten, its physical state has been altered, but it is still within the system. The work and heat produced by the base runner are not created by him; they are derived from the chemical bond energy of the food he has eaten.

   The basic equation for energy relations is: ΔG = ΔH - TΔS.  Δ is the standard symbol for an increment or amount of change. DG stands for change in free energy, which means energy available to do work, not a free lunch. The concept was developed by Willard Gibbs, a professor of physical chemistry at Yale, and probably the best scientist ever born in America. H is heat; T is temperature on the absolute or Kelvin scale, and S is entropy, an indicator of disorder in a system. There is no device for measuring S; it is always calculated.  ΔG can be obtained from redox potentials and from equilibrium concentrations of chemicals in a reaction mixture. ΔH is found from temperature measurements. And I am not making this up. It is best not to use the word entropy unless you are actually working on problems in thermodynamics.

   Energy budgets are expressed in joules (jewels, not jowls), the SI units comparable to calories. 1 joule is the amount of work done when 1 kg is lifted 1 meter, in other words, the energy expended to move this weight in opposition to the force of gravity. It is such a small amount that the answers to energy problems are usually in kilojoules (kJ).

   Glucose burned in a calorimeter yields the same products, CO2 and H2O, and the same amount of energy, 17 kJ per gram, as glucose metabolized by living cells. Mass and energy are conserved in both processes.

   For those accustomed to working with calories, the conversion factor is:     1 kcal = 4.186 kJ. The Calories listed on cereal boxes are really kcal. The label states that 30 g toasted oats contains 110 Cal. To compare with the content of glucose above:

   110 kcal / 30 g = 3.667 kcal / g;  3.667 X 4.186 kJ / kcal = 15.35 kJ / g.

Since cereal is mostly carbohydrate, it is not surprizing to find a value equal to 90 % of the glucose value.

Exercise 13-1. The basal metabolic rate (BMR) of the “average” (70-kg) adult male is 7 410 kJ per day.With moderate activity, the rate  rises to        11 720 kJ / day. Calculate the weight of oat cereal needed to maintain these metabolic rates.

   Of course, the supply of energy is not the whole story of human nutrition.  Adequate water and salts, essential amino acids, vitamins, all are important. Also desirable are a good cook and a pleasant dinner companion.

   Power is the rate of doing work, expressed as 1 J / s = 1 Watt. Much of the early work on thermodynamics emerged from the work of Watt on steam engines.  Joule was recognized for his work on the mechanical equivalent of heat. Cecie Starr wrote that heat production by humans is similar to the heat output of a 100-Watt light bulb. Since the number of seconds in a day is: 60 X 60 X 24 = 86 400 s / day, the BMR above becomes  7 410 kJ / 86 400 s = 0.08576 kJ / s = 85.8 W.

Exercise 13-2. With the metabolic rates above, calculate the power in Watts of the standard man when moderately active.

   In spite of the equal net effects of combustion and metabolism, the chemical reactions are totally different. There is no such thing as a “fat-burning” fitness scheme.  The living machine makes ATP (adenosine triphosphate) at ordinary body temperature, a molecule that powers muscular contraction, breaks down in the process, and is then resynthesized. The ΔG of ATP hydrolysis is -30.56 kJ/ mol (-7.3 kcal).  By convention, ΔG is negative when energy is available to do work, and positive when energy must be put into the system to produce a reaction. As Mathews wrote, “evolution has created an array of enzymes that preferentially bind ATP, and

use its free energy of hydrolysis to drive endergonic reactions.”

   The empirical formula of ATP is C10H16O13N5P3. Adding up all the atomic weights gives a molecular weight of 507.488; thus 1 mole weighs 506.488 g. Compared to glucose, the energy of ATP is very small:

   1 g / 506.488 g/mol X 30.56 kJ/mol = 0.0602 kJ / g. This emphasizes the point that ATP is not a fuel; it is part of the cellular machinery, a carrier of chemical bond energy to the sites where energy is needed.

   Large amounts of kinetic energy are released in explosions. 1 ton of TNT has been reported to release 5 X 106 kJ. A ton of 2 000 lbs. is the same as 907.19 kg. Therefore:

E = 5.51 kJ / g, about 1/3 as much energy as glucose, but much greater power, because it is released suddenly.

   Until 1900, mass and energy were entirely separate concepts, and the motion of electrons around the nucleus of an atom resembled a miniature solar system. First the quantum mechanics of Max Planck, and then the relativity of Albert Einstein, changed all that. The general public left quantum theory to the physicists, but they loved the idea of relativity. Einstein did not like the word; he was interested in absolutes. He liked women, and disliked haircuts (Fig. 13-1), which made caricatures almost too easy (Fig. 13-2).

   This book is about useful calculations, not theoretical physics.   Interconversions of mass and energy are not conspicuous features of everyday life, but they do occur. The production of C-11 in a cyclotron (Chap.10) is an example of conversion of energy to mass. Conversion of mass to energy occurs in the radioactive decay of uranium to lead; one intermediate step is the radium-to-radon transition (Chap. 10). The conversion was first demonstrated conclusively in a nuclear reactor, then shown in a spectacular way in atomic bombs, and now occurs regularly in nuclear power plants.

   In the equation E = mc2, E is energy (kJ) and m is mass (kg) and c is a constant equal to the speed of light, 3 X 108 m/s. Ever since it became clear that the speed of light can be measured, some physicists have been interested in obtaining more and more precise values of c, a recent one: c = 2.99792458 X 108 m/s. This is only slightly more practical than calculating p to one thousand places.

   The fission of U238 has been reported to liberate 200 MeV (million electron volts) per atom. After several conversion factors are applied, this works out  to 8.097 X 107 kJ/g.

According to the basic equation:

E = 0.001 kg (3.0 X 108 m/s)2 = 8.988 X 1010 kJ/g.

From this, it is apparent that only a small fraction of the mass of uranium is converted to energy, but that fractional amount, compared to other energy sources, is enormous.

Exercise 13-3. Compare the energy content of 1 gram of toasted oats, TNT, and uranium.

   There is some conversion of mass to energy outside of nuclear power plants. If a 10-Watt flashlight is left “on” for a long time, there is a small loss of mass:                10 W = 10 J/s

m = E/c2 = 10 / (3 X 108 m/s)2 = 1.1126497 X 10-16 kg  per second.

Seconds in one year = 60 s/min X 60 min/hr X 24 hr/d X 365.2 d/y =

3.1553 X 107 s/y.

Δm/y = 3.1553 X 107 X 1.113 X 10-16 = 3.5107 X 10-9 kg = 3.5107 µg/y.

   An analytical balance can measure a change of 0.1 mg or 100 micrograms. The time required to make the loss of mass from the flashlight perceptible:

      Δt = 100µg / 3.5107 µg/y = 28.48 years.

This is really just playing with numbers, a game that theoretical physicists love to play.

Chapter 14. Summary

   The topics chosen for this book have sampled arithmetic, geometry, algebra, and a bit of calculus. The goal was to provide a kind of “liberal arts” experience for students who might be inclined to seek ways of avoiding mathematics. The liberal arts are those “befitting a free man”. In the modern sense, they consist of the humanities, social sciences, and natural sciences. In the classical sense, the liberal arts were exactly seven: a trivium (grammar, rhetoric, and logic), and a quadrivium (arithmetic, geometry, astronomy, and music). The number of departments in a college or university corresponds to the number of ways in which knowledge can be divided. Not to hurt anyone's feelings, some subjects are basic, and some are not. Mathematics is certainly one of the basics. A technician is someone who knows his job, and a bit more.  A philosopher is someone who knows everything, and nothing more. A mathematician is someone who makes new mathematics. A scientist is someone who wants to see the data, and wants to know what conclusions   are implied by the data. A liberal artist is someone who likes discussion, and believes that he or she can be successful at virtually any task.

    Several chapters have shown how much physics and chemistry depend on mathematics. Other books have shown how empty they are without it.   Students in the arts and humanities need some minimal education in math and science in order to communicate with people outside their own specialty, to bridge the gap between the “two cultures”. A truly educated person is fluent in three languages: (1) his native language, (2) a foreign language, needed to appreciate how grammar and rhetoric vary, and (3) mathematics, the universal language of engineers and scientists. In the modern world, being “innumerate” is a deficiency like being illiterate.

   This book is intended to help students learn how to solve problems that have numerical answers, with the aid of a scientific calculator. It is not intended to serve as preparation for further study of mathematics. Exponents and logarithms are included to the extent that they are useful. The goal is not  to stimulate deeper enquiry, although it is acceptable if that happens. Bits of the history of mathematics serve as snacks, not as the main course. If a  mathematician criticizes this work for lack of rigor or originality, she is missing the point.